<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some observations upon the late tryals of Sir George Wakeman, Corker and Marshal [i.e. William Cuthbert Wall], &amp;c. by Tom Tickle-foot the taborer, late clerk to Justice Clodpate.</title>
            <author>Smith, Francis, d. 1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A71049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4540</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5156</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11936254</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11936254</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51185</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A71049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51185)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 513:41, 903:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some observations upon the late tryals of Sir George Wakeman, Corker and Marshal [i.e. William Cuthbert Wall], &amp;c. by Tom Tickle-foot the taborer, late clerk to Justice Clodpate.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Francis, d. 1688.</author>
                  <author>Wakeman, George, Sir, fl. 1668-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>9 [i.e. 11] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Brewster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Tom Ticklefoot the taborer is Francis Smith.  Cf. BM, v. 238, col. 941.</note>
                  <note>Entry for W277 cancelled in Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wakeman, George, --  Sir, fl. 1668-1685 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Corker, James Maurus, 1636-1715 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Wall, William Cuthbert, 1625?-1704 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51185:1"/>
            <p>SOME OBSERVATIONS Upon the Late TRYALS OF Sir GEORGE WAKEMAN, CORKER and MARSHAL, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Tom. Tickle-foot</hi> the Taborer, late Clerk to Juſtice <hi>Clodpate.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—In tempore dicere verum Quis vetat?</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Brewſter.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51185:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51185:2"/>
            <head>SOME OBSERVATIONS Upon the Late TRYALS OF Sir <hi>George Wakeman, Corker,</hi> and <hi>Marſhal,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Reader may perhaps wonder why I ſhould wave the Employment of Clerking to a <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, who ſeldom are of the wiſeſt; and turn Minſtrel; but upon ſerious thoughts he will reſpect me for my Integrity, and give greater faith to what I ſhall offer now; for to ſay the truth, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of my former life were ſo villainous, in order to my Calling, as I could no longer diſpenſe with them; for I was forced to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form my maſter's Worſhip of all the Bawdy-Houſes within his Diſtrict, which by that means were all ſet under Contribution, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51185:3"/>out of their Compoſitions for Enormities I had Poundage, which was all my ſubſiſtance; for his Worſhip-engroſſed all the Warrant-Revenue to himſelf, ſo I grew of late melancholy, through the fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Trade, the private Miſſes driving all before them, that publick Sinners are now of all people the moſt miſerable; ſo I retired ſome time before my Maſter's death, in which Retirement, as Barbers having nothing to do, learn to play on the <hi>Cittern,</hi> I got a ſtroke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pipe and Tabor, by which means I now live very comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, yet willing to give the world a Taſte of my old Office of Clerk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I have made theſe following Obſervations.</p>
            <p>The firſt part of the Tryal was ſpent in the examination of <hi>Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale, Prance</hi> and <hi>Jenniſon,</hi> to prove the Plot, ſo to obviate the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon objection, that it was unreaſonable to believe two men againſt ſo many, upon bare teſtimony without other Circumſtantial E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, that was done with ſuch notoriety, as ſatisfied all unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced perſons: amongſt other things it was proved by an undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Witneſs, Mr. <hi>Jenniſon,</hi> corroborated with notable Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that <hi>Ireland</hi> died with a Lye in his Mouth, as by conſequence Sir <hi>John Southcot</hi> and his Lady lives with the ſame veracity, which my old Maſter would have made another kind of uſe on than was made; then was ſome fine Harangues about it to anſwer ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, yet nothing was reduced to practiſe in the Caſe, during that part of the Tryal in which the Priſoners were but remotely concerned; it may be obſerved, that <hi>Corker</hi> fell into great undecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of paſſion, againſt the Witneſs <hi>Dugdale,</hi> an argument of Guilt my old Maſter would have ſaid; yet no Inferences nor Reproofs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. Now I have given a ſhort, yet true account of what was but preliminary to <hi>Wakeman</hi>'s, and their Tryals, I ſhall go on, Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> proved, that <hi>Wakeman</hi> refuſed ten thouſand pounds, as too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for poiſoning the King, which he termed ſo great a Work, and afterwards did undertake it for five thouſand more, as it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten down in the Entry Book, kept ſometimes at <hi>Wild Houſe,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at <hi>Langhorne</hi>'s Chamber; and further, as appeared by the ſaid Entry Book, there was five thouſand pounds paid in part, and a Receit ſubſcribed, <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> which by a compariſon of Hands was ſworn to be Sir <hi>George</hi>'s Hand, which Sir <hi>George</hi> ſhifted off by the help of an Apothecary, as he thought well enough; yet granting the Apothecary to ſay true, which is queſtionable too, for they are often ſlippery Chapmen, eſpecially conſidering former Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: and future hopes, and <hi>Oates</hi> to ſwear true, which no wife man will diſpute, there might be two Letters, which Sir <hi>George</hi> would ſtur off, from the improbability of writing two Letters to one thing, and gravely bids the Jury take notice, that he writ but one Letter, he might with the ſame modeſty have adviſed them not to believe a word againſt him, yet little notice taken.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51185:3"/>
            <p>The improbability of writing two Letters to one thing ſeemed to weigh ſomething with the Lord Chief Juſtice: Though not ſo with Juſtice <hi>Pemberton,</hi> who ſaid it might be ſo, <hi>To ſerve a turn very well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was proved likewiſe by Doctor <hi>Oates,</hi> that <hi>Wakeman</hi> had a Commiſſion to be Phyſician General to the new Army, which my Lord Chief Juſtice had like to have forgotten.</p>
            <p>Amongſt other matters, <hi>Bedlow</hi> depoſed, that Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> came into <hi>Harcourt</hi>'s Chamber in a Chafe, and told him, he knew not whether he ſhould go on or no, <hi>Harcourt</hi> went to his Cabinet, and took out a Bill, and asked Sir <hi>George</hi> if he was ready, Sir <hi>George</hi> ſaid he was, and had been long ſince, but they were not punctual with him. But what have you there a Bill for two thouſand pounds at your ſervice, replyes <hi>Harcourt;</hi> which Bill Sir <hi>George</hi> accepted, and afterward told <hi>Bedlow,</hi> that the Goldſmith had allowed of it, and would pay him in the Afternoon, when <hi>Wakeman</hi> objected, it was not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſhould diſcover ſo great a ſecret upon ſo ſmall an acquaintance: <hi>Bedlow</hi> replyed, he would have a hundred times more, if <hi>Harcourt</hi> had but told him he was his Confident, as he had done then. <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> rambled out into a paſſion, and ſwore, that he never ſaw him in all his life, yet <hi>Bedlow</hi> made it out by circumſtances, that he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Phyſick of him at the <hi>Bath;</hi> and that acquaintance he did not deny, but called him Rogue, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Before the Priſoner called his Witneſs, it may be obſerved, that the Lord Chief Juſtice ſaid, that <hi>Bedlow,</hi> the ſecond Witneſs, ſaid no material thing againſt <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> but only ſome Circumſtantials about a two thouſand Bill, but not ſaid for what, ſome things about the Queen his Lady and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Robert Sawyer</hi> replyed under favour, and began to ſum up <hi>Bedlow</hi>'s Evidence, ſo the Lord Chief Juſtice ſeemed not pleaſed, and anſwered what is all this? call Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> again, to whom he made a godly ſpeech about innocent Blood, and bade him give his evidence anew, who gave what is aboveſaid. Sir <hi>George</hi> replyed, what if the Queen had given me two thouſand pounds for my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice done her, is that any harm? I have deſerved I am ſure for nine years Service; yet a little before a proteſtation before God he never ſaw <hi>Bedlow,</hi> a likely matter, as if an abſolute Stranger ſhould come to the knowledge of ſuch a Money-Circumſtance; and agree in the Sum too: <hi>Bedlow</hi> went on, and ſwore, that <hi>Harcourt</hi> ſaid to Sir <hi>George,</hi> This muſt be well followed, and cloſely obſerved, becauſe much depends upon it: <hi>For if we ſhould miſs to kill him at.</hi> Windſor, <hi>or you miſs in your way, then we will do it at</hi> New-Market. The Lord Chief Juſtice made <hi>Bedlow</hi> report the words again, which he did, only interpoſing (Which we hope you will not:) The Lord Chief Juſtice replyed very modeſtly, he ſays now quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing; but was contradicted by the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>North,</hi> the Recorder, &amp; Sir <hi>Robert Sawyer,</hi> &amp; ſubmitted to it moſt Chriſtianly.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51185:4"/>Then <hi>Bedlow</hi> went on, and ſwore, that Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> in his hearing, declared his conſent; and that it was one entire diſcourſe, upon which the Knight, as well he might, ſaid to the Priſoners, <hi>Then is my buſineſs done,</hi> and he had been a true Prophet, if either Wit or Honeſty had exerciſed a due dominion over the Jury: Now if my old Maſter <hi>Clodpate</hi> had been on the Bench, he would have hung hard upon that expreſſion, as alſo upon Sir <hi>George</hi>'s allowing of two thouſand pounds to be paid for Wages, he would have ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered it, and have ſaid, this is not to be ſaid to us that know the Methods of the Court, never to pay ſo much Wages at a time, they always inſtal ſuch Summs; you might however have brought ſome other authority beſides your ſelf, which can deſerve no credit here, when it is clear by all Circumſtances, you invoked God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to a Lye, about your never ſeeing <hi>Bedlow</hi> within theſe ten Minutes.</p>
            <p>Againſt <hi>Corker, Oates</hi> depoſeth, that he ſaw his Patent from <hi>Rome</hi> to be Biſhop of <hi>London;</hi> that he was privy, and did conſent to <hi>Langhorne</hi>'s Propoſal to the <hi>Benedictine</hi> Monks, to advance ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds towards carrying on his Deſign, his conſent being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, becauſe he was Preſident; and that <hi>Corker</hi> ſhould ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he carried on the Deſign under the diſguiſe of beſtowing the Queen's Charity; and that he did except againſt <hi>Pickering</hi> being choſen to kill the King, being that a mere Lay-man was more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi> was charged with the ſame thing, and that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal</hi> went half with <hi>Conyers,</hi> who layed a Wager that the King would eat no more Chriſtmaſs Pyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bedlow</hi> depoſed further againſt <hi>Corker,</hi> that he had heard him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about raiſing an Army, but nothing poſitively to the Murder of the King. <hi>Bedlow</hi> accuſed <hi>Marſhal</hi> much about that rate; but <hi>Marſhal</hi> not being ſhye of his lip-labour, fell to impertinent queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, about his knowing him, but was confuted, but not at all aſhamed in his Lyes by Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> who was ſworn in the Caſe; but <hi>Marſhal</hi> with a company of ſoft words, would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded Sir <hi>William</hi> that he forſwore himſelf; the Prieſt ſurely loved to hear himſelf prattle, to ſpend ſo much time to the waſting of his credit, about a thing which was not of a Farthing Concern, true or falſe: then he asked <hi>Bedlow</hi> whether he had ever ſeen him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was taken. Who ſaid, at the <hi>Savoy.</hi> Then with an unheard of impudence he replyed, he would be content to be hanged, if <hi>Bedlow</hi> could prove, that he was ever at the <hi>Savoy. Bedlow,</hi> though he had none by to prove that, as perhaps he would have been in the ſame caſe, if he had been to have proved himſelf ever to have been in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> as the L. C. J. intimated; yet he did it by a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Circumſtance, when he gave Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> directions where to ſearch for the Gun that was to have killed the King, which was found accordingly. This is now the ſubſtance of what the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, <hi>Wakeman, Corker, Marſhal</hi> were charged with: the other, <hi>Rumley</hi> had but one Witneſs againſt him, ſo went off on courſe, Sir
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51185:4"/>
               <hi>George</hi> now called his Witneſs, the Chief was <hi>Chapman</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary, of which I have given a former account. Then was his man <hi>Hunt,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth Henningham</hi> called, who talked at the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary's rate; ſo that <hi>Oates</hi> was not at all contradicted by them, but they might both ſay true, and that the C. J. told them. Then Sir <hi>Philip Loyd</hi> was called upon by Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> to adjuſt what Doctor <hi>Oates</hi> ſhould ſay at the Council Table, who ſaid, but not upon Oath, that when Sir <hi>George</hi> was called in before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and told of his Accuſation, he utterly denyed all, <hi>and did indeed carry himſelf as if he were not concerned at the accuſation.</hi> Then <hi>Oates</hi> was called in to tell what he knew further; for as yet he had given but a hear-ſay evidence (as my old Maſter uſed to term it) he reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with lift up hands, <hi>God forbid (for I muſt tell truth,</hi> ſays Sir <hi>Phil. Lloyd, let it be what it will) that I ſhould ſay any thing againſt Sir</hi> George Wakeman; <hi>for I know nothing more againſt him. Oates</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, he knew nothing at all of this. Sir <hi>George</hi> triumphed, and cryed, this is a Proteſtant Witneſs. Now had old Juſtice <hi>Clodpate,</hi> my old Maſter, been upon the Bench, he would have taken up the Knight, and told him, he had given a very officious Teſtimony; for he was to tell only what <hi>Oates</hi> ſaid at that time, and not to pretend to skill in Phyſiognomy; for he was not mealy mouth'd, but would up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion have talked his mind to Knights, or any Body, and would have ſaid further, it appears to me, and may appear to any body elſe, that this Knight has as great a kindneſs for Sir <hi>George,</hi> as for truth, and bidden the Jury have obſerved accordingly; he would not have left there neither, for he would have ſaid, admit Sir <hi>Philip</hi> ſays true, and that is as kind to him as can be, what would Sir <hi>George</hi> infer? that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> is now tyed up in his Evidence, by no means, for the Caſe is no more than if a man be brought before a Juſtice of Peace for ſtealing a Cow, and that Witneſs makes a ſolemn proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he knows no more againſt him, yet afterwards upon his Arraignment ſwears to a Horſe too, in another Bill of Indictment, the former aſſeveration is atteſted by his Worſhip's Clerk, <hi>quaere,</hi> whether that will quit him for the Horſe, or ought to be ſo much as heard in a Court? Beſides here has been a late judged Caſe, <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread</hi> and <hi>Fenwick</hi>'s, the Jury was withdrawn for want of full evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence afterwards one of the ſhort came to ſwear home, and was admitted, the Priſoners found, and executed accordingly, if that was right, as no queſtion it was, becauſe practiſed, as I have been informed, it muſt be much more in the right now, to admit of <hi>Oates</hi> his further Teſtimony; for the Council-Table is no Court of Record as this is.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Doleman</hi> was called in for <hi>Oates,</hi> who ſaid, that <hi>Oates</hi> at that time was in great diſorder and confuſion, and as feeble as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he ſaw any body in his life, ſo as he believed he could not give any body a good anſwer; and further ſaid, that <hi>Wakeman</hi> was called in, and gave his Anſwer, at which the Council was amazed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51185:5"/>for he did not in his opinion deny it ſo poſitively as one that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent could, but ſhuffled matters off with expreſſions of the great Loyalty and Services to the Crown of himſelf, and Family, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired reparation for injury done. It ſeems Sir <hi>Philip</hi> and Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> had different ſentiments about Sir <hi>George</hi> his meene. When Sir <hi>Thomas Doleman</hi> had done, Sir <hi>George</hi> unbidden fell into a repetition of what he had ſaid at the Council Table in his defence, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved only into a telling what a Gowen he had been for the King, what work his Brother made at <hi>Worceſter;</hi> how his Father loſt eighteen thouſand pounds Eſtate for the King, how he was in a Plot for the King, was taken at his <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> ſome Arms found in the Cellar, carried to Priſon, and in much danger of being hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and how his Family was mighty inſtrumental in the ſaving of the King, as Colonel <hi>Gifford,</hi> his Cozen <hi>Carlos,</hi> and that the <hi>Pendrels</hi> were menial Servants to the Family.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Corker</hi> was called, who began with a florid diſcourſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the Witneſſes, that they had been men of ſcandalous lives, and that there was no Plot, which he flouriſhed off as well as he could, but not to any reaſonable ſatisfaction; then he came to trifling about going to <hi>Lamſpring</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and ſuch other ſmall matters; but at laſt he ſaid, he was not Preſident of the <hi>Benedictines;</hi> which was material, had it been well proved, for it obviated Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> his Accuſation of conſenting to the ſix thouſand pounds as Preſident. Then <hi>Marſhal</hi> was called to ſay for himſelf, who made a great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about a white ſpot under his Perriwig, and Sir <hi>William Waller</hi>'s ordering him to put it off, and many inferences he would have made, and then made a great ſtir about Witneſſes he could have come within three days, and many good morrows to no purpoſe. Then <hi>Corker</hi> called his Witneſs <hi>Nell Rigby,</hi> to prove that he was in the <hi>Savoy</hi> when <hi>Pickering</hi> was taken; and that <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> did know ſo much: ſhe likewiſe averred, that <hi>Stapleton</hi> was Preſident of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> and <hi>Corker</hi> never officiated as ſuch, and that ſhe ſaw Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> once in the Houſe, who came a begging to Mr. <hi>Picke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> for charity, and that was in the midſt of the Plot, as was made out by circumſtance, from whence <hi>Marſhal</hi> inferred, it was not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſhould truſt him with any thing of that nature, and ſuffer him to want. This now muſt be a new contrivance, for it would have been ſet up before in <hi>Pickering</hi>'s Tryal, had there been any thing of truth in it. I now wonder, that none from the Bench ſet upon that Bitch Fox, to run down her teſtimony, for allow that to be true, the <hi>Plot is Non-ſuit, Semel inſanivimus omnes;</hi> my old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter would have clawed the three penny Baggage, and told her her own, and likewiſe have broke her credit with the Jury, by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that it was never before offered, a thing that they could not be ſo careleſs in, had the thing been true. Now Miſtreſs <hi>Sheldon</hi> was called to prove <hi>Stapleton</hi> Preſident of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly did ſo. Then <hi>Alice Broadhead</hi> did the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51185:5"/>
            <p>Then Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> was called again, but never examined, he is wiſe that can tell why; without ſome-body was afraid he ſhould have clear'd the Point, as it was formerly in another caſe about Mr. <hi>Howard</hi>'s Son.</p>
            <p>Then the Court asked them if they had done all three? Sir <hi>G. Wakeman</hi> fell to a deteſting, forſwearing, and abominating the <hi>Plot,</hi> and that he had never a farthing for any ſuch thing. <hi>Corker</hi> much at that rate: And <hi>Marſhall</hi> made an Harangue, that had it not been for my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>North,</hi> I believe would have laſted till now; it was all full of proteſtations of the Innocence of the Executed perſons; which were fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by the Ch. J. <hi>Sc.</hi> Who after ſome little trifling veli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations with the Prieſts, ſumm'd up the Evidence. In the firſt part he proved by Mr. <hi>Jeniſon,</hi> as has been hinted before, that <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> dyed with a lie in his mouth.</p>
            <p>Now a man would wonder what he ſhould urge that for, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to infer, That if dying men in their laſt breath wou'd lie, why ſhould living perſons be believed under their circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; eſpecially, when a Jury is free by the Law to do what they will without blemiſh in the caſe.</p>
            <p>Then the C. J. goes on and ſums up <hi>Oates</hi> his Evidence againſt <hi>Wakeman,</hi> which his Lordſhip leaving or forgetting all the material Points, makes onely circumſtantial: Till Sir <hi>Robert Sawyer</hi> put him in mind of his Commiſſion, ſeen by <hi>Oates,</hi> to be Phyſitian to the new Army; and then his Lordſhip goes on, and allowes that, as likewiſe that he refuſed 10000 l. and would have 15000 to do the Work; but with an unuſual ſweetneſs, leaves <hi>the Truth with the Jury,</hi> and then falls moſt Religiouſly into a declarement a gainſt ſhedding innocent blood: which he did ſo pathetically, as no man would judge him to be the Son of a Father, who, as Moderns ſay, was not very ſcrupulous in that point.</p>
            <p>Then he goes on to Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi>'s Evidence, and though he ſumm'd it up a little ſhort, yet he makes him a ſecond Witneſs againſt <hi>Wakeman,</hi> if the Jury will believe him. <hi>Now conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe [Ifs] were never put before, why the Devil ſhould they now, would Old</hi> Clodpate <hi>have ſaid; and ſo ſay I</hi> Tom Tickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot.</p>
            <p>And then the Chief Juſt. prayes the Bench in ayd, if he had forgotten any thing material.</p>
            <p>Then his Lordſhip was pleaſed to ſay the Evidence againſt <hi>Corker</hi> was not full, ſo as to prove any Fact, but only ſome Words; and that he was not Preſident of the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> his Lordſhip affirmed from the Teſtimony of three Fling-ſtinks, without any manner of hint to the Jury, that they were not upon their Oaths; The Charge againſt <hi>Marſhal,</hi> his Lordſhip ſaid was rather leſs then againſt <hi>Corker,</hi> and ſo accordingly lightened it, as became him.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51185:6"/>
            <p>Then he comes to Sir <hi>Phillip Lloyd</hi>'s Teſtimony, which he laid as great a ſtreſs upon, as it would naturally bear; and ſo as to invalidate any further teſtimony againſt Sir <hi>George Wakeman,</hi> his Lordſhip was pleaſed to name Sir <hi>Thomas Doleman</hi>'s Evidence, but with ſo little reſpect, as he might have, as decently, let it alone: And to invalidate <hi>Oates</hi> his Teſtimony further, he takes notice that he was begging, without intimation to the Jury, of any probability of the matter, which muſt utterly deſtroy Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> for the future; for no body that believes that, can believe any thing he ſayes of the <hi>Plott.</hi> And then after a Pious Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Jury to take care of Innocent bloud, he concludes, telling them, <hi>That if they believe</hi> Oates <hi>and</hi> Bedlow, <hi>they may do well to find; otherwiſe not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bedlow</hi> charged the Chief Juſtice for not ſummoning up his Evidence right; Who onely replyed, He knew <hi>not by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority this Man ſpeaks.</hi> I ſhall only make this Obſervation upon his Lordſhip, In all former Tryals he went on without the leaſt heſitation or running the ſame over again, as he did not in this, eſpecially about the concern of innocent bloud: But by all that's good, it was my Old Maſter <hi>Clodpate</hi>'s diſeaſe, peace be with him, alwayes to Sham up an Evidence when any body had bin with him the Morning before.</p>
            <p>About an hour after the Jury returned and brought e'm in not guilty; but according to their abundance of want of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, enquired whether they might not bring e'm in guilty of Miſpriſion or no? Now could ſuch a thing come into their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique pates, had they underſtood what the word meant? for that implyes a knowing of, but not conſenting to a Treaſon. Now there was no manner of colour for ſuch a thing; for the Evidence was full, if they believed them, as to abſolute Treaſon: If not, why would they think of any thing but Acquittal? But it may be they knew not the force of the word, which led them into that Errour; I'm ſure that's their beſt Plea; otherwiſe they muſt yield themſelves to be great betrayers of their Nation, and ly under a damn'd ſuſpition of being fouly practiſed upon; Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if that be true that runs about in Coffee-Houſes, That a Gentleman, that went out amongſt e'm, had a ſealed Paper of 50 Guineys thruſt into his hand.</p>
            <p>They ſay in the <hi>North,</hi> That a Jury conſiſts of Eleven Fools and a Knave. Now thoſe of the <hi>South,</hi> as being more refined Wits, are of a nobler conſiſtence, as having more of the Knave in them. For had they had a mind to have examined matters, and not barely to have acquieſt in outward appearance, they might have conſidered, That <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow</hi> did not ſwear by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice like the Boys of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> from this circumſtance, That <hi>Rumley</hi> had but one Witneſs againſt him. Now had Hanging, and not Truth been the deſigned matter, how eaſie a thing had it been for Captain <hi>Bedlow</hi> to have agreed with Dr. <hi>Oates,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51185:6"/>made up two witneſſes againſt <hi>Rumley,</hi> is obvious to every conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Capacity, and might have play'd ſuch a prank formerly to have ſerv'd a turn, when they were liſted amongſt the Pope's <hi>Mamalukes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no ſmall wonder, I confeſs, to <hi>Tom Ticklefoot,</hi> that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from the Bench nor Barr hinted that Circumſtance; my Old Maſter <hi>Clodpate</hi> would have been hanged before he would have miſſed ſuch a Barn-dore.</p>
            <p>I am more particular in this, to the end that circumſtance of their not Combining, may induce Juries for the future, to look upon them, as Men that ſwears onely according to the dictates of Truth, notwithſtanding the Sham Tale of the Doctor's begging at <hi>Pickering's.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
